Guide to the Joshua E. Clayton Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joshua E. Clayton papers
1864-1892
WA MSS S-1355
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3
(4 boxes)
The collection consists primarily of Clayton's reports on mines and mining districts in California, Colorado, Montana, Nevada, and Utah. There are also a variety of papers, including correspondence, documenting mining in Montana, Nevada, and Utah.
Other Storage Formats: Oversize
Clayton, J. E. (Joshua Elliot)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of the Joshua E. Clayton Papers were donated by Charles and Lindley E. Eberstadt in 1959 and 1963. Charles Eberstadt donated the report on the Granite Mountain Lode and Stephens Mining Property (Box 1, folder 39) in 1959 and Lindley donated the other mining reports and the correspondence in 1963. The origin of the other material (primarily the section "Other Documents Regarding Mining") is unknown, except for the 1853 agreement which was donated by Charles and Lindley Eberstadt in 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 4: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Scope and Contents
The Joshua E. Clayton Papers document the career of a mining engineer working primarily in the western United States. The collection spans the period 1864-1892, but the bulk of the collection covers Clayton's mining interests during the 1860s and 1870s.
The papers are arranged in three sections. Clayton's Reports on Mining Properties contains statements he prepared on various mines and mining districts in California, Colorado, Montana, Nevada, and Utah. Other Documents Regarding Mining consists of various agreements, assay certificates, and other papers which Clayton collected. Correspondence contains letters written both to and by Clayton as well as other documents directly related to the correspondents.
Clayton's Reports on Mining Properties is arranged chronologically. An attempt has been made to identify the mining district, county, and state for the mine or area described (brackets [] were used in folder titles to identify supplied information). Most of the reports are in the form of letters written in pencil and may represent drafts or copies Clayton made for his files. Generally the reports include the following data: a description of the property's location using geographic features and often naming the district and county; a geological description of the area; a detailed report on the location and direction of the vein, surrounding rock, and any development work (tunnels, etc.); and estimates on the value of the property as well as recommendations for development. The majority of the reports are for mines and districts in Utah.
Other Documents Regarding Mining, arranged chronologically, contains a variety of papers documenting mining in Montana, Nevada, and Utah. All the items for 1865 concern claims in the Union Mining District, Nye County, Nevada. The 1866 file consists of assay certificates issued by Theall & Co., of Austin, Nevada, for samples deposited by Clayton. The 1869 file contains a draft agreement for development work on a mine in the Gold Mountain Mining District, Nye County, and 1872 contains an agreement for the transfer of mining property in White Pine County, Nevada. In 1883 Clayton drafted a prospectus for the Bannack Mining & Reduction Co. Ltd. to mine for a variety of ores in Beaverhead County, Montana. Along with this description of the proposed company and the mineral wealth of the area, there is a contract to sell property in the area to Bannack. The 1883 file also contains Clayton's appointment to the National Mining and Industrial Exposition Association and an article from Salt Lake City's Daily Tribune reporting Clayton's idea for a state mining association. In 1884 this idea came to fruition and the Salt Lake Mining Institute was founded with Clayton as its first president and general manager. The collection contains two drafts of his address to the people of Utah describing the purpose of the Institute. Clayton wanted the Institute to establish a museum and library on Utah's mineral resources.
Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by correspondent, also focuses on Clayton's mining career. The collection includes copies of his letters to Samuel B. Martin concerning a mining operation in Silver Peak, Nevada. Clayton, who appears to be the supervisor or manager, describes the hauling and mill machinery and there is a receipt for supplies purchased by Martin for "S.P.& R.M.G.& S.M. Co." Letters from W. B. Odgen also concern the Silver Peak mine. The collection contains Clayton's correspondence with the secretary of the Original Hidden Treasure Mining Company while he was superintendent in 1870. John R. Park, president of the University of Deseret, exchanged letters with Clayton, as president of the Salt Lake Mining Institute, concerning museum management. Alexander Wakefield's letters and legal papers document his involvement with Clayton in the business side of mining. Other correspondence has been filed in folder 61. Most of the letters refer to mining properties and reports. An 1882 letter from Clayton to Governor Murray reports on his work as Utah's commissioner to the National Mining and Industrial Exhibition.
Oversize material has been filed in Box 3.
Mines and mineral resources -- California; Mines and mineral resources -- Colorado; Mines and mineral resources -- Nevada; Mines and mineral resources -- Utah; Lander County (Nev.); Salt Lake County (Utah); Tooele County (Utah); Mining engineers -- Nevada; Mining engineers -- Utah; Clayton, Joshua E. (Joshua Elliot); Martin, Samuel B.; Ogden, W. B.; Park, John R.; Wakefield, Alexander; National Mining and Industrial Exposition Association; Original Hidden Treasure Mining Company; Salt Lake Mining Institute
- Clayton's Reports on Mining Properties, 1864 Sep 10
  - Manning Claim, Bobby Burns Claim (El Dorado County, California), 1864 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Milwaukee Lode, Vanderbilt Lode (Reese River Mining District, Lander County, Nevada), 1865 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - North Star Hill Consolidation and Tunneling Company properties (Reese River Mining District, Lander County, Nevada), 1865 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - San Francisco Tunnel (Reese River Mining District, Lander County, Nevada), 1865 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mines of the district (Union Mining District, Nye County, Nevada), 1865 Apr 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Amador Mine (Amador Mining District, Lander County, Nevada), 1865 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Northern Star and other lodes (Union Mining District, Nye County, Nevada), 1865 Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Lode (Mariposa County, California), 1865 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Covington Lode, Pullman and Thomas Ground (Reese River Mining District, Lander County, Nevada), [1865] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Silver Peak Mining District (Esmeralda County, Nevada), 1866 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pocotillo Mine (White Pine Mining District, [White Pine County], Nevada), 1871 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chicago Mine (Ophir Mining District, [Toole County], Utah), 1872 Feb (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - North Star Mining District ([Beaver County], Utah), 1872 Mar 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rush Valley Mining District ([Toole County], Utah), 1872 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Alpha Mine (Little Cottonwood Mining District, [Salt Lake County], Utah), 1872 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ontario Mine (Uintah Mining District, [Wasatch County], Utah), 1872 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Eureka Hill mining locations ([Tintic Mining District, Juba County], Utah), 1873 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chicago Silver Mining Company smelting works ([Ophir Mining District, Toole County], Utah), 1873 Aug 11 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Last Chance Mine ([West Mountain Mining District, Salt Lake County], Utah), 1873 Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Davenport Mine ([Little Cottonwood Mining District, Salt Lake County], Utah), 1874 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ophir Hill Mines ([Ophir Mining District ?, Toole County, Utah), 1874 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Neptune Mine (West Mountain Mining District, Salt Lake County, Utah), 1874 Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Whatcheer Lode ([Salt Lake County ?], Utah), 1874 Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Flagstaff Mine (Uintah Mining District, Summit County, Utah), 1874 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chicago Mine ([Ophir Mining District, Toole County], Utah), 1874 Jun 6 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Balsam Mine (Ophir Mining District, [Toole County], Utah), 1874 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Queen of the West Lode ([Utah County ?], Utah), 1874 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Neptune and Kempton Mine ([West Mountain Mining District, Salt Lake County], Utah), 1874 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Neptune and Kempton Mine (West Mountain Mining District, Salt Lake County, Utah), 1874 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Emma Hill Consolidated Mining Company claims ([Utah]), 1875 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Yosemite Mine ([Utah County ?], Utah), 1875 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Superior Mine (Little Cottonwood Mining District, [Salt Lake County], Utah), 1875 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Great Basin Lode, Queen Lode (Rush Valley Mining District, Toole County, Utah), 1879 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Jordan Mine ([West Mountain Mining District, Salt Lake County], Utah), 1880 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hudson Mining Claim ([Salt Lake County], Utah), 1880 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Morning Star Claim, Victoria Mine (Lander County, Nevada), 1880 Aug 20, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Red Elephant Mountain Mines (Colorado), 1880 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Stephens Mining Property (Montana), 1881 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Granite Mountain Lode (Montana), 1881 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cave Mine, Carbonate Mine (Beaver County, Utah), 1882 Jun 1 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Rebellion Mine ([Summit County], Utah), 1882 Jun 30 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Lowell Mine (Unitah Mining District, [Wasatch County], Utah), 1883 Dec 31 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Eureka Hill ore deposits ([Tintic Mining District, Juba County], Utah), 1885 Jun 29 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Ontario Mine([Unitah Mining District, Wasatch County], Utah), 1888 Mar (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Mining properties near New Henley (Siskiyou County, California), [1892?]
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Notebook, Box 1, folder 38.
  - Elgin Mine (Big Cottonwood Mining District, [Piute County] Utah), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Other Documents Regarding Mining, 1853
  - Agreement, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Abstract of title to mining claims, agreements, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Assay certificates, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Agreement, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Assay certificate, 1870
    See: Oversize, Box 3, folder 63
  - Agreement, report by W. L. Faber, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    See also: Oversize, Box 3, folder 64
  - Assay certificate, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Proposal for mining company, newspaper article, agreement, Clayton's appointment to National Mining and Industrial Exposition Association, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Clayton's address to the People of Utah as president and general manager of Salt Lake Mining Institute, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Assay certificate, envelope, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Correspondence, 1867-68
  - Martin, Samuel B.: letters from Clayton, 1867-68 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Martin, Samuel B.: account for S.P.& R.M.G.& S.M. Co., 1867 Aug 31 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Ogden, W. B.: letters to Clayton, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Original Hidden Treasure Mining Company: correspondence with Clayton (superintendent), 1870 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Park, John R.: correspondence with Clayton, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Warfield, Alexander: letters to Clayton, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Warfield, Alexander: legal documents, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Other correspondence, 1866-82 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Oversize, 1870
  - Assay certificate, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Report by W. L. Faber, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 63)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Scope and Contents
  Box 4, Restricted Fragile Papers, contains fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 30 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Box 2, folder 52 (Box 4, Folder 65)